Curriculum Vitæ- Diego Zamboni

October 6, 2017 — short version

Personal information

Full name: Diego Martín Zamboni

Email: diego@zzamboni.org
Web: http://zzamboni.org/

LinkedIn: http://mx.linkedin.com/in/zzamboni

Twitter: http://twitter.com/zzamboni

Introduction

I possess a strong combination of theoretical and practical knowledge in mul-

tiple areas of computing that make me able to analyze complex problems and both design and implement elegant solutions. I am a team player and a natural leader. I am self-motivated and have excellent communication skills in both Spanish and English, including ample experience in technical writing, teaching and public speaking. I have a strong and rich background, including advanced education, scientific research, practical technical knowledge and customer-facing experience.

Areas of interest and expertise

Systems architecture and development:

Unix/Linux systems engineering and administration, cloud computing environments (OpenStack, Amazon EC2), software development experience (C, Perl, Ruby, Java, Go, Python, Clojure).

Computer security:

Intrusion detection and prevention, operating systems security, network security, software security, secure software development, virtualization and cloud computing security, malware detection and containment.

Configuration management and automation:

I am a CFEngine 3 expert, author of "Learning CFEngine 3" published by O'Reilly Media, and have knowledge of other configuration management systems including Puppet, Chef and Ansible. I am very interested in the area of self-healing systems and architectures.

Other skills:

Excellent written and spoken communication skills, customer-facing experience, project and product management experience.

Work experience

January 2017 to date: Squad Lead and Product Owner in the Enterprise Service Cloud project at Swisscom.

I work with Product Management to define the technical features necessary for Health Management and Monitoring in the Enterprise Service Cloud project, and lead the team which implements, deploys and operates these components.

March 2016 to date: Head of Health & State Management at Swisscom.

I lead a team of people working on multiple projects related to Health Management and monitoring/logging of the Swisscom cloud offerings.

June-December 2016: Lead of Squad LEMM in the Enterprise Cloud project at at Swisscom.

I lead the architecture and delivery of the Logging, Event Management and Monitoring framework (LEMM) of the Swisscom Enterprise Cloud.

August 2015–March 2016: Cloud Architect and Orchard Project Lead at Swisscom.

I continued leading the *Orchard* project through its implementation, release and further improvements and development.

This is a short version. The full version of this document can be found online at http://zzamboni.org/vita.html.

August 2014-July 2015: Senior Platform Architect (consultant) at Swisscom Cloud Lab.

I designed the architecture for the *Orchard* health-management and self-healing components of Swisscom's "Application Cloud" Platform as a Service Offering. This system performs self-monitoring and self-healing of the infrastructure and platform components. In addition to designing the architecture, I worked on its implementation together with a team of three people managed by me.

July 2012–July 2014: Director de Investigación y Capacitación (Head of Research and Training) at Boundless Innovation and Technology.

I advised and coordinated teams working on teaching- and security-related products, consulting and services.

August 2013-June 2014: Product Manager at CFEngine AS.

I coordinated the CFEngine Design Center, participated in the development of the CFEngine language roadmap, and coordinated the work on CFEngine third-party integration.

October 2011-June 2014: Senior Security Advisor at CFEngine AS.

I worked as an overall advocate and fanatic for CFEngine, with a special focus on security. I also worked on developing and implementing the strategy for CFEngine in security.

October 2010-October 2011: Account Security Officer at HP Enterprise Services Mexico.

In this position I was the first point of contact for all security-related issues for five HP enterprise customers in Mexico, some of them with international presence.

November 2009–October 2010: IT Outsourcing Service Delivery Consultant at HP Enterprise Services Mexico.

My role was to help customer teams by solving complex problems in customer environments.

October 2001-October 2009: Research staff member at the IBM Zurich Research Laboratory.

The focus of my work was in intrusion detection, malware detection and containment, and virtualization security. See *Research activities* for details of research.

August 1995–August 1996: Founder and head of Computer Security Area National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM).

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science: August 1996-August 2001.

Purdue University, Department of Computer Sciences.

Thesis title: *Using Internal Sensors for Computer Intrusion Detection.*

Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.

M.S. in Computer Science: August 1996-May 1998.

Purdue University, Department of Computer Sciences.

Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.

Publications (sample)

Books: Diego Zamboni. *Learning CFEngine 3*. O'Reilly Media, Inc., March 2012. ISBN 9781449312206. URL http://cf-learn.info/.

Editorial activities: From 2011–2013 I was a member of the Editorial Board for the Computers & Security Journal.

Diego Zamboni and Christopher Kruegel, editors. *Recent Advances in Intrusion Detection: 9th International Symposium, RAID 2006, Hamburg, Germany, September 20-22, 2006, Proceedings (Lecture Notes in Computer Science).* Springer-Verlag New York, Inc., Secaucus, NJ, USA, 2006. ISBN 354039723X.

Deborah Frincke, Andreas Wespi, and Diego Zamboni. Guest editorial: From intrusion detection to self-protection. *Computer Networks*, 51(5):1233-1238, 2007. ISSN 1389-1286. URL http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.comnet.2006.10.004.

Refereed papers:

Urko Zurutuza, Roberto Uribeetxeberria, and Diego Zamboni. A data mining approach for analysis of worm activity through automatic signature generation. In *Proceedings of the 1st ACM workshop on AISec (AISec'08)*, pages 61–70, New York, NY, USA, October 2008. ISBN 978-1-60558-291-7. URL http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1456377.1456394.

Diego Zamboni, James Riordan, and Milton Yates. Boundary detection and containment of local worm infections. In *Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Steps to Reducing Unwanted Traffic on the Internet (SRUTI'07)*. Usenix, June 2007. URL http://www.usenix.org/events/sruti07/tech/full_papers/zamboni/zamboni.pdf.

James Riordan, Diego Zamboni, and Yann Duponchel. Building and deploying Billy Goat, a worm-detection system. In *Proceedings of the 18th Annual FIRST Conference*, June 2006.

Florian Kerschbaum, Eugene H. Spafford, and Diego Zamboni. Using internal sensors and embedded detectors for intrusion detection. *Journal of Computer Security*, 10(1,2):23-70, 2002. URL http://iospress.metapress.com/content/rkylmv8hepn2p71d/.

Certifications

SAFe® 4 Certified Product Owner/Product Manager, July 31st, 2017.

A SAFe® 4 Certified Product Owner/Product Manager is a SAFe professional who works with customers and development organizations to identify and write requirements. Key areas of competency include identifying customer needs, writing epics, capabilities, features, stories, and prioritizing work in order to effectively deliver value to the enterprise.

Foundation Certificate in IT-Service Management (ITILv2), April 2006.

IBM Micro MBA program, March 2003.

Research activities

Selected research projects at IBM:

Project Phantom: (2008-2009) Security for VMware virtual environments using virtual machine introspection.

Code instrumentation for intrusion detection: (2007) Exploration of code instrumentation and low-level monitoring mechanisms for intrusion detection.

Billy Goat: (2002–2008) An active worm-detection system.

Router-based Billy Goat: (2005–2007) An active worm-capture device.

SOC in a Box: (2005–2007) Integrated device containing multiple security tools.

Exorcist: (2001–2002) Host-based, behavior-based intrusion detection using sequences of system calls.

Ph.D. thesis research:

Utilization of internal sensors and embedded detectors for intrusion detection.

Additional projects: Using autonomous agents for intrusion detection.

Analysis of a denial-of-service attack on TCP/IP (Synkill).

Software development

Programming language experience: C, Perl, C++, Java, AWK, Unix shells (Bourne, C shell, Korn shell), Python, PHP, Ruby, Objective C, Cocoa (MacOS X), Go, Clojure.

Environments: Unix/Linux, OpenStack, Amazon EC2, Mac OS X.

Other experience: Riemann (event stream processing), XML and related technologies, network programming, database programming (SQL), kernel programming (OpenBSD and Linux), HTML.

Major publicly-available software projects: CopperExport, mailer, AAFID₂ prototype

System administration experience

Unix systems: Linux, OpenBSD, FreeBSD, MacOS X, MacOS X Server, Solaris.

Configuration management: CFEngine 3, Puppet, Chef, Ansible.

 $Virtualization, \ container, \ cloud \ and \ SDN \ platforms: \\ OpenStack, Amazon \ EC2, Docker, VM ware \ (ESX \ and \ vSphere), Plumber \ (ESX \ and \ vSphere),$

grid.

Security systems and software: Snort IDS, Bro IDS, Nessus vulnerability scanner, HoneyNet platform, Nepenthes mal-

ware collection platform.

Other professional activities (sample)

2011–2013: Member of the Editorial Board for the Computers & Security Journal.

2010–2012: Member of the Cfengine Champions (C³) program, which recognizes outstanding contributions to the

CFEngine community.

2007–2012: Member of the Steering Committee for the International Symposium on Recent Advances in Intrusion

Detection (RAID).

2009: Program chair for the 2009 workshop of the Zurich Information Security Center (ZISC).

2008: Program chair for the SIG SIDAR Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability

Assessment (DIMVA).

2006: Program chair for the 9th International Symposium on Recent Advances in Intrusion Detection (RAID).

Spoken languages

Spanish (native), English (near-native spoken and written fluency), German (medium), French (basic).

References Available by request.